<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jake.nabasny.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://jake.nabasny.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-09-02T19:43:23+00:00</updated><id>https://jake.nabasny.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website of Jake Nabasny, PhD.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Eudaimen Ethics - Aristotle</title><link href="https://jake.nabasny.com/memo/2024/Aristotle-Eudaimonia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eudaimen Ethics - Aristotle" /><published>2024-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jake.nabasny.com/memo/2024/Aristotle-Eudaimonia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jake.nabasny.com/memo/2024/Aristotle-Eudaimonia/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://books.google.co.uk/books/publisher/content?id=9T2OAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PP1&amp;img=1&amp;zoom=3&amp;hl=en&amp;bul=1&amp;sig=ACfU3U0_ZxFDhO8i7Y2pgIhKLdjpD5Uozw" alt="cover" /></p>

<h1 id="eudaimen-ethics">Eudaimen Ethics</h1>

<p>by Aristotle</p>

<h2 id="publishers-summary">Publisher’s Summary</h2>
<!-- No more than a couple paragraphs summarizing this BOOK -->

<blockquote>
  <p>Aristotle’s moral philosophy is a pillar of Western ethical thought. It bequeathed to the world an emphasis on virtues and vices, happiness as well-being or a life well lived, and rationally motivated action as a mean between extremes. Its influence was felt well beyond antiquity into the Middle Ages, particularly through the writings of St. Thomas Aquinas. In the past century, with the rise of virtue theory in moral philosophy, Aristotle’s ethics has been revived as a source of insight and interest. While most attention has traditionally focused on Aristotle’s famous Nicomachean Ethics, there are several other works written by or attributed to Aristotle that illuminate his ethics: the Eudemian Ethics, the Magna Moralia, and Virtues and Vices.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="notes">Notes</h2>
<!-- The main content of my thoughts really -->

<h4 id="introduction">Introduction</h4>
<p>11-2 Aristotle not concerned with morality in the modern sense</p>
<h4 id="text">Text</h4>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>33 happiness is most noble, best of all things, and pleasantest
- possible paths to happiness: nature, learning (knowledge), training, divine influence, fortune
34 every person has an overarching telos
35 mix of experience and reason is necessary to find good life
41 happiness = "best of what are matters of human action"
42 ANTI-PLATO: Idea of good cant direct action
44 Idea of good not "useful"
45 virtue = best state/task of object, person, etc.
- ex. garment
46 task/ergon = action, project, deed
- task &gt; state (hexis): so its more about what you do than who you are
- ex. cobbler's virtue
47 def. happiness
- happ. is activity/use
49 excess vs. deficiency
- ex. food
51 golden mean
53 virute spectrums are abstract states corresponding to a variety of concrete manifestations
54 states/capacities are related to emotions, which are distinguished by pleasure and pain
57 only humans can act
58 virtue/vice only apply to voluntary acts
59 3 types of desire: will, passion, appetite
61 voluntary action is deliberative
- desire and reason both play a part in human action
62-3 pleasure and pain exist in both vice/virtue
65 def. of voluntary: all a man does without being ignorant, on his own initiative, and having the power not to do so (last is most interesting, and prob why A analyzes the problem of incontinence so much)
68 def. of choice
- choice "arises out of deliberative belief"
69 process of deliberation
70 argument connection virtue/vice to pleasure/pain (not directly, obviously; see p. 62)
- moral virtue = mean; vice = excess or deficiency
- "vice [...] is concerned with the same matters as virtue"
78 "virtue implies choice"
93 justice = complete virtue; because best man is not he who is only virtuous to himself but also to others
97 justice = proportion
98 justice = rectification
105 justice applies to the different and multiple, not the selfsame!
106 universal vs. particular
111 contrary to popular belief, acting just is NOT easy: "Men think that acting unjustly is in their power, and therefore that being just is easy. But it is not: to lie with one's neighbour's wife, to strike one's neighbour, to offer a bribe, is easy and in our power, but to do these things from a certain state of character is neither easy nor in our power."
- ex. easy to bribe, cheat, etc., but not as easy to be just
- being just requires specific knowledge of "how actions must be done and distributions effected" and is more than just knowing what is good (e.g. health)
- ex. specific causality of healthy objects
111-2 unjust (and just) acts require real effort, the kind that builds character: "to act unjustly consists not in doing these things, except coincidentally, but in doing them from a certain state of character, just as to practise medicine and to heal consists not in applying or not applying the knife, in using or not using drugs, but in doing so in a certain way."
113 no universals, only probability, when it comes to action
117 calculate = deliberate
- reason must be true and desire must be correct for choice to be virtuous
118 action (good and bad) requires both thought and character
- 5 kinds of knowing: craftsmanship, knowledge, wisdom (phronesis), understanding, intelligence
119 def. knowledge
- craft = producing; =/= action
120 phronesis = good deliberation
- concerns what can be otherwise
- production vs. action
121 "wisdom is a virtue not a craft"
123 good action = deliberation on universals and particulars
124 universals and particulars
- phronesis is same disposition as art of politics
- phronesis is like a political reason foucsed on the individual alone
- phronesis directs oneself; justice directs other
126 correctness in deliberation, NOT belief or knowledge
- not just WHAT, but HOW
127 judgement vs. wisdom/phronesis: both concern deliberative problems, but only wisdom issues commands for action (a key diff between ethics and morality!!)
128 sympathy is a "similar sense" of another and ground of equity
- in greek, "sense" is part of "sympathy" (as in, similar sense) cf. Schopenhauer
- universals reached from particulars
129 raw experience is just as much of a guide to universals as demonstration!
130 virtue is the aim; wisdom is the means
- goodness requires a state that involves both wisdom and virtue
131 "it is impossible to be wise without being good"
135 "the wise man is a man of action"
138 particulars, not universals, concern action
- incontinence is a misapplication of the universal to the particular
- knowledge takes time and becomes part of us
143 excess vices are either brutish or diseased
148 depravity/vice = disease; incontinence = epilepsy (i.e. momentary)
- virtue/vice encourge/destroy our PURPOSE respectively
152 habit is like nature, but not identical (both can be changed)
160 friendship is a kind of "private justice" wholly in our power
164 three types of friendship basis: utility, virtue, pleasantness
166 universal and personal good must align; politics forces this alignment for those who don't have it
167 "the task of every capacity is external; for it is in something different or in oneself *qua* different"
170 "all have some good in them" (e.g. singers)
174 good = simple, self-identical, static
178 only adults can be good/friends to themselves because they have the "power of choice", which children and animals lack
189 living = knowing
196 phronesis is not knowledge, but "another kind of cognition"
202 two kinds of good fortune: divine (consistent) and natural (inconsistent). both lack reason.
203 combo of all virtues = gentlemanliness
- the goods that all strive for (honor, riches, bodily virtues, power, good fortune) can be harmful to people without the right "states of character"
204 gentlemen deserve "riches, high birth, and power" in virtue of their noble character. these things are not noble for most people, who dont have the character to virtuously wield these goods
- "complete virtue" - deeds done for the sake of virtue itself
206 ultimate ethical goal: "to perceive the irrational part of the soul, as such, as little as possible"
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Jake Nabasny</name></author><category term="notes" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="aristotle" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Individuation in Light of Notions of Form and Information - Gilbert Simondon</title><link href="https://jake.nabasny.com/memo/2024/Simondon-Individuation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Individuation in Light of Notions of Form and Information - Gilbert Simondon" /><published>2024-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jake.nabasny.com/memo/2024/Simondon-Individuation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jake.nabasny.com/memo/2024/Simondon-Individuation/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://books.google.co.uk/books/content?id=9mG6zwEACAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;img=1&amp;zoom=1&amp;imgtk=AFLRE71f96Q4dbmpegSL3VPiEI_gmcGcTl2jKg-C5nkk2eMQYnllYXsy4LDAWr_IFNjxJKHGNPOQY6Nz1BVTL1P-xPgDjOJnU6sxCQwMNoN-Daw-ApxhIRHDNZh4-2zbgH5lJgpgtaSB" alt="cover" /></p>

<h1 id="individuation-in-light-of-notions-of-form-and-information">Individuation in Light of Notions of Form and Information</h1>

<p>by Gilbert Simondon</p>

<h2 id="publishers-summary">Publisher’s Summary</h2>
<!-- No more than a couple paragraphs summarizing this BOOK -->

<blockquote>
  <p>A long-awaited translation on the philosophical relation between technology, the individual, and milieu of the living From Democritus’s atomism to Heisenberg’s uncertainty principle, from Aristotle’s reflections on the individual to Husserl’s call for a focused return to things, from the philosophical advent of the Cartesian ego and the Leibnizian monad to Heidegger’s notion of Dasein, the question concerning the constitution of the individual has continued to loom large over the preoccupations of philosophers and scholars of scientific disciplines for thousands of years. Through conceptions in modern scientific areas of research such as thermodynamics, the fabrication of technical objects, gestalt theory, cybernetics, and the dynamic formation at work in the creation of crystals, Gilbert Simondon’s unique multifaceted philosophical and scholarly research will eventually lead to an astounding reevaluation and questioning of the historical methods for posing the very question and notion of the individual. More than fifty years after its original publication in French, this groundbreaking work of philosophical theory is now available in its first complete English language translation.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="notes">Notes</h2>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>5 more than a unity or identity
6 indiviudation (ID) is mediation
9 social is higher order metastability (cf. Spinoza)
10 knowledge generated by problematics, not sensation
11 information as relation that spurs ID
13 failure of classical logic
- def. transduction
14 transduction is "mental procedure"
17 ID of knowledge is knowledge of ID
22 technical operation required to rbing form to matter
28 clay "takes" form in communication with worker; doesn't "receive" form from the mold
30 hylemorphism is the knwoledge of a technical object by someone who is outside the workshop
32 ID ends in equilibrium
33 decacy sets in when ID finishes
35 representation of technical ID is candidate for knowledge of virtal ID (cf. 17)
38 tool-use is also about reading matter through signals in the tool
40 ex. pores of wood
41-3 implicit forms
- ex. statistically predictable implicit forms
42 technical operation integrates implicit forms
44 workers vs. bosses
47 singularities exist in an inter-zone
- individual is an *activity* of a relation
53-4 critique of Spinoza and Leibniz
56 Potential Energy (PE) as exemplar for study of ID
- PE is virtual, not just possible; relation in itself, not substance
- relation vs rapport
57 ID requires "true relation"
68 strucutral PEs as formal conditions of possible geneses
- crystals show ID prior to substance, quality, and quiddity
70 ID operates as a state modification, not identity
- history
71 complete ID = exhaustion of PE
72 lesson of physical ID is not the *types* of individuals, but the infinity of individuals that can come from one structural *type*
73 particular beings never belong to types
74 active consistency
75 form = macro
   matter = micro
75-6 against correlationsim: being is a relation, and our knwoledge of it is a relation to this relation, so we can learn about relation by studying our own knowledge of being
76 epistemological postulate
- "approximate knowledge" as metastable version of "exact knowledge"
77 thought = relation with historical aspect
85 properties are relational, not substantial
87 goal of the study
- an epistemology anterior to any logic
93 ID creates a system, not substance
97 ancient physics was too often driven by ethical motives
- Christianity "liberated" physics by providing a "non-physical foundation to ethics"
107 veritable analogy = identity of rapports, not rapport of identity
- difference, not resemblance
108 transductive method = application of veritable analogical reasoning
- scientific thought as distribution, not classification or identification
109 ex. transductive method = discovery of electromagnetic spectrum
110 def. general individual
- "allagmatic epistemology"
111 not dialectics
- domains of thought are horizontal, not hierarchical
116 ex. real analogy = light as electromagnetic wave
118 ex. TV
120 psychosocial vs. transductive view of TV
121 analogy not resemblance
- topology not hierarchy
131 Becoming is integrated in Being
- limit of interiority is limit of being, i.e. relation
132 against interiority and monads
152 PE **exists**
- ID qua ID is such only by relation to non-individuated real
- "Relation always exists as potential"
- relation = energetic exchange
153 against Descartes
158 photon =/= individual
- condition of veritable individual
159 individual is not simultaneous to itself
- substance vs physical being
160 preindividual is first reality
163 quantum vs. substantial difference
- viruses
- single vs. multiple input beings
164 vital ID is *slower* than physical
- neoteny of animal/plant life
167 methological postulate for vital ID
- quantum measure, not quantity
- vital unit can be discrete individual or a group
168 vital individual is mortal
169 real analogy vs. inductive classification
170 complex organisms have less integrative potential
171 information in physical vs. biological individuals
172 automoton vs. vital being: latter has capacity for transduction
173 "most conspicuous biological transduction" = reproduction
- vital growth/reproduction is not physical since it "combines with speciated individuality"
176 aestheticism
177 psychical is a "slowing down" of ID
- not "higher arrangement" but a "new plunge into preindividual reality"
178 malformed psyche
182-4 against Freud
- types of "death"
185 not dialectics
- "evolution is a transduction"
- heredity
196 Weismann's germ-plasm
199 final position on regeneration vs. reproduction
209 individual is act, not being
- both result and agent
- hereditary substance
- recapitulation (neoteny)
210 criterion of individual functional autonomy is hereditary substantiality
211 "the regime of information [...] defines the degree of individuality"
212 individuality is marked by: a type of act or event with the possibility of reaction, and an autonomous zone that permits it
222 becoming other
223 polarity
- living is what reproduces itself
225 energy in the living vs. inert
226 constructive vs. peaceful equilibrium
236 "To live consists in being agent, milieu, and element of ID"
237 no pure interiority
238 entropy of successive IDs
240 entelechy = collective ID
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Jake Nabasny</name></author><category term="notes" /><category term="science" /><category term="technology" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="simondon" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ethics - Benedict de Spinoza</title><link href="https://jake.nabasny.com/memo/2024/Spinoza-Ethics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ethics - Benedict de Spinoza" /><published>2024-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jake.nabasny.com/memo/2024/Spinoza-Ethics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jake.nabasny.com/memo/2024/Spinoza-Ethics/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://books.google.com/books/content?id=YUjuAAAAMAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;img=1&amp;zoom=1&amp;source=gbs_api" alt="cover" /></p>

<h1 id="ethics">Ethics</h1>

<p>by Benedict de Spinoza</p>

<h2 id="publishers-summary">Publisher’s Summary</h2>
<!-- No more than a couple paragraphs summarizing this BOOK -->

<blockquote>
  <p>Published shortly after his death, the Ethics is undoubtedly Spinoza’s greatest work - an elegant, fully cohesive philosophical system that strives to provide a coherent picture of reality, and to comprehend the meaning of an ethical life. Following a logical step-by-step format, it defines in turn the nature of God, the mind, the emotions, human bondage to the emotions, and the power of understanding - moving from a consideration of the eternal, to speculate upon humanity’s place in the natural order, the nature of freedom and the path to attainable happiness. A powerful work of elegant simplicity, the Ethics is a brilliantly insightful consideration of the possibility of redemption through intense thought and philosophical reflection.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="notes">Notes</h2>
<!-- The main content of my thoughts really -->

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>#### I: God/substance
2 attributes determine identity
3 causal relation establishes commonality
	There is nothing but substances and their affections
5 modifications do not exist outside intellect
	Clear and distinct = true
	Existence/essence of substance is eternal truth
6 more reality = more attributes
7 God exists
8 perfection and existence increase/decrease in unison
10 only substances and modes exist
	Body = "any quantity, with length, breadth, and depth, limited by some certain figure"
15 essence vs. existence
16 God is immanent cause of all things
19 particular things are just affections/modes of God's attributes
	Modes are nothing but affections of God's attributes
20 remote causes
	Natura naturata (passive nature) vs. natura naturans (active nature)
21 intellect is a mode of thinking (differing from desire, love, etc.)
	Will is a mode of thought, and is not free
	"we can understand nothing that does not lead to more perfect knowledge of the intellection"
22 God doesn't "create" anything (anti-Creationism)
	Necessary vs. impossible
23 contingency is a defect of knowledge
	Ascribing freedom to God is a "great obstacle of science"
	God could never decree anything different
25 summary of God's properties
27 mathematics allows humanity to attain divine knowledge
	"All final causes are nothing but human fictions"
29 "the will of god, that is, the sanctuary of ignorance" (contra intelligent design)
29-30 human values determined by what is most pleasing to us
30 good/evil judgments are based on human preferences (via imagination)
	People also like to imagine that God likes/establishes harmony
	The imagination is the source of all this error, and distracts from the actual nature of things
31 for the majority of people, perfection = what is most pleasurable/useful

#### II: human mind and body
31 body is conceived in a "certain and determinate way"
32 ideas are concepts, not precepts
	Adequate vs. true
	Collective agency
34 God's power must not be confused with human power or right of kings
	Ideas not caused by object or perception, but by God
35 necessary path of implication: attribute of thought -&gt; ideas -&gt; objects
	Immanence of the "order and connection" of ideas and things
	Thought and extension are "one and the same substance" explained through different attributes (monism)
	Ideas must be explained through thought alone; things through extension alone
36 EMERGENT PROPERTIES
37 causal chain always leads back to God
38 first priority of philosophy: investigate God
	First constitutive element of a human mind is an idea
39 the object of this constitutive idea is the human body (both of which exist in God)
40 human exists with both mind and body, which are united
41-3 physical doctrine of bodies
	Bodies differentiated by speed and slowness
	Simple vs. composite bodies
	Speed is more important to identity than substance or parts
	Nature can be thought of as a single individual composed of many parts
44 postulates of the human body
	V: skin and memory, inscription
	The mind perceives everything that happens in the body
	Atomism of ideas (each idea composed of partial ideas)
45 causality requires similar nature
	Correlationism: ideas of external bodies indicate our own body more than anything outside of it (and reference to Appendix I)
	Memory
	Habit, leads to error
46 definitions of image and imagine
	Imagination does not always lead to error
	Relation between imagination and habit (in producing error)
	Definition of memory
47 two orders of connection: affections vs. ideas
	Linguistic arbitrariness of the sign thesis
	Relativity of imagination leads to different habits and associations
	Ex. Farmer vs. soldier
	Mind does not know body exists, only knows its affections
48 order and connection of ideas same as for causes (monism)
	Idea of idea: ideas are nested in each other
49 mind perceives affections of body and ideas of these affections
	Mind does not know itself, except through ideas of bodily affections
50 external bodies determine the human body in a certain way (as in structuralist differential signification?)
	Correlationism; External reality is imaginary
51 ideas of affections are confused ideas ("conclusions without premises")
	Ideas arrived at through the body lead to a "mutilated and confused" knowledge
52 internal ("agreements, differences, and oppositions") vs. external (ideas of affections) knowledge
53 free will theory based on ignorance of the cause of one's actions
54 inadequate ideas follow with same necessity as adequate ones
	Things that are common to all must be conceived adequately
56 confused origin of TRANSCENDENTALS and UNIVERSALS (via imagination)
	Even these notions are relative to an individual's experience
57 FOUR LEVELS OF KNOWLEDGE: random experience, opinion or imagination, reason, intuition
58 "true idea involves the highest certainty"; truth is the standard of itself (59)
59-60 time is imaginary
60 modes involve the concept of their attribute (i.e. you can always trace the cause from the effect)
62 no free will
	No absolute faculties (any distinction among mental faculties are "complete fictions")
	Reference to Appendix I
	Definition of will: affirming to denying something. ("Not the desire by which the mind wants a thing or avoids it")
63 definition of idea: a concept of thought, not an image
	The will is the intellect
64 goal of this doctrine is to be able to "arrange one's life wisely," and to speculate
	Ideas involve affirmation or negation
	Word and images are merely "corporeal motions," not concepts of thought
66 perception is not indifferent
67 not sure how highly we should esteem suicides, children, fools, and madmen
67-8 ethical and social benefits of the doctrine (foreshadowing of final chapter)

#### III: emotional psychology, or the affects
69 nature has no defect
	Affects (emotions) are part of nature and work by the same necessity
	Human actions and appetites must be analyzed like "planes, lines, and bodies"
70 definition of affect: increase/decrease in power of acting (or idea of this power)
	Affect is either action or passion
	Body retains "traces" of objects
	By having adequate ideas, the mind also "acts"
71 more inadequate ideas correlate to more passions; more adequate ideas to more actions
	Monism
72 body operates partly autonomously from mind
	Ex. Animals, sleepwalkers
73 infant, angry child, timid, drunk, madman, chatterbox, child
	Decision and determination are really the same
	Decision requires recollection/memory
74 free decisions are imaginary; those who believe in them "dream with open eyes"
75 no self-destruction
	CONATUS Principle: each thing strives to preserve in its being
	This striving = actual essence of thing
76 will vs. appetite: will is striving of the mind; appetite is striving of mind and body, thus the "very essence of man"
	Appetite = desire
	Definition of desire: "Appetite together with the consciousness of the appetite"
	"we neither strive for, nor will, neither want, nor desire anything because we judge it to be good; on the contrary, we judge something to be good because we strive for it, will it, want it, and desire it."
77 joy (passing to greater perfection) vs. sadness (passing to lesser perfection)
	These are both passions, also can be called pleasure/pain, cheerfulness/melancholy
	Three primary affects: joy, sadness, desire
	Mind strives to imagine what increases its power
78  imagination leads to affects in the body
	Love vs. hate (both related to an external cause)
	Habit/imagination can lead to imaginary/ghostly affections: felt, but not really existing
	Imagination of the mind indicates affects of the body more than existence of external objects
80 vacillation of mind: experience of contrary affects
81 hope, fear, confidence, despair, gladness, remorse
82 pity, favor, indignation
83 pride: "a species of madness" where "the man dreams, with open eyes"
84 overestimation, scorn, imitation/emulation
	We strive to free from suffering things we pity
85 benevolence, ambition, human kindness, praise, blame
86 love of esteem, shame, self-esteem, repentance
	Agreement with others empowers our preferences or dislikes
87 desire to have similar preferences as others
	The same nature that makes men compassionate also makes them envious/ambitious
	Children are proof of this entire emotional psychology
89 longing
91 affect is origin of judgement (cf. 76)
	Timidity, sense of shame, consternation
92 anger, vengeance, reciprocal love, thankfulness/gratitude, cruelty
93 "hate…can be destroyed by love"
94 class hatred and racism (just part of our nature) [EUGENIC LOGIC!]
95 love for free things &gt; love of necessary things; so, men love each other more than things
	Good/bad omens
96 principle of difference (all affects and people are different)
	There are as many judgements as affects
	Intrepid, daring, timid, cowardly
97 repentance and self-esteem can be very "violent"
	Wonder, veneration, consternation, dread, devotion, disdain
98 mockery, contempt
	The mind empowers itself as it more distinctly conceives of and rejoices in its power
	Mind strives to only imagine empowering things
	Humility, self-love, self-esteem (onto 99)
99 inherent competition: natural inclination to hate and envy
	Education bolsters competition, since parents teach children to value honor/envy
	Virtue = power of acting
100 every object produces its affect in a different way (as many species of sadness or whatever as there are objects)
	And just as many species of desire
	Gluttony, drunkenness, lust, greed, ambition: not affects or passions, since they have no opposite
101 "desire is the very nature, or essence, of each [individual]"
	Joy and sadness are markers of the increasing or decreasing of desire/appetite (either toward greater or lesser perfection)
102 for each species, their own affects 
	Exs. : horse, insects, etc. ; gladness of a drunk vs. of a philosopher
	All of the past discussion concerned passions, the rest concerns actions
103 moderation, sobriety, presence of mind in danger, courtesy, mercy
	Our contingent fortune makes us feel like we are lost at sea (Stoic metaphor!)
	Enjoyment leads to a new constitution
	Ex. Food and drink, leading to disgust, weariness
104 "appetite is the very essence of man, insofar as it is determined to do what promotes his preservation"
	Joy/sadness is necessarily a PASSAGE
105 primitive or primary affects: joy, sadness, desire
107 pity = compassion
108  right and wrong
	Developmental psychology, children, education
	Relativity of experience/values based on education
109 those we believe to be most humble are usually most envious 
111 cruelty opposed to mercy
	Ambition is always present in desire
112 full definition of affect

#### IV: Bondage/power of affects
113 def. of bondage: fortune &gt; autonomy
114 changing definition of perfection
	Universals complicit in relative perfection
	Appendix I
	Final cause = human appetite
115 humanity conscious of appetite but not its cause (cf. Schopenhauer's principle of will)
	Reality = perfection
	Appendix I
	Good and evil only modes of thinking
	Definition of Good and Evil
116 Beings change according to perfection ("passage"), not essence
117 virtue = power = essence of man
118 human perseverance to exist is limited
119 "the affect stubbornly clings to the man"
120 power struggle of the affects (immanent forces)
	Good and evil = affects (of joy and sadness)
121 Good/evil only conceptually distinct from affect
	Time limits affective force (more present = stronger)
123 truth can't influence affect except as an affect itself (affect &gt; knowledge)
124 goal of investigating reason is determining limits of action
125 dictates of reason
	Virtue = acting from natural laws
	Foundation of virtue = self-preservation
	Virtue is its own reward
	Prohibition of suicide (since contrary to foundation)
	We can never live without dealing with things outside us
126 self-interest is just, honorable, and basis of morality
126-7 only external causes lead one away from self-preservation
	Suicide is the result of external causes dominating
127 "striving to preserve oneself is the first and only foundation of virtue"
128 acting = living = preserving our being
	Only what leads to understanding is useful
129 mind's greatest virtue = to know God
130 a thing is good if it agrees with our nature
131 man is changeable
133 man who helps himself also helps others
	Virtuous action is rational action
134 definition of morality (and honor)
	Friendship
135 contra animal rights
	We can use animals as we please
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Jake Nabasny</name></author><category term="notes" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="spinoza" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Tooth - Rachilde</title><link href="https://jake.nabasny.com/memo/2024/Rachilde-The-Tooth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Tooth - Rachilde" /><published>2024-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jake.nabasny.com/memo/2024/Rachilde-The-Tooth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jake.nabasny.com/memo/2024/Rachilde-The-Tooth/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-tooth">The Tooth</h1>
<h3 id="by-rachilde">By Rachilde</h3>

<p>In passing by chance the dining room, she saw, on a dresser, a dozen
pistachio croquets, and, mechanically raising her hand up to the silver
plate that supports the appetizing pyramid, she chose the driest and
most glazed, with an inexplicable gluttony… since she is not a
glutton. Suddenly, in crushing the pastry, she felt a hard object, a
small object much harder than the pistachios, and at the same moment a
vibration had run through her entire body, a strange vibration that went
spiraling from her gums to her heels. What? What is this? She removes it
with the tips of her two nails. How! a pebble in a croquet from the good
creator! She approaches the pale green stained-glass window, behind
which extends a dreamy field, all green and pale, then she examines the
pebble very closely with a cold, subtle breath on her hair. It, it’s a
tooth!</p>

<p>Horror sweeps her off her feet; she falls to her seat, her pupils
dilated. A tooth! Hers. No, no, it’s impossible! Come on, she would have
been suffering already, and she never had a toothache. She is still
young, she takes scrupulous care of her mouth, all while having, it must
be admitted, a profound disgust for the dentist. She probes, there, on
the side, a little behind the smile, and finds that there is a hole. She
leaps up, strikes the stained-glass window with her forehead, looks with
irritated eyes at this little object which gleams with a slightly
yellowish whiteness. Yes, in fact, it’s a tooth; it is crowned with a
dark trim at the spot of the break. Worn down, but how long has it gone
on for? Attacked by what? It did not cause her any suffering at first,
and now she found herself plunged into one of those despairs which, for
lasting only one day, are all the more terrible. From now on she has a
defect! A door has just opened on her thoughts, and she will no longer
know how to keep certain words from coming out, without her wanting it,
of her mouth. She isn’t old; however Death has just inflicted on her his
first flick of the fingers.</p>

<p>Throwing the remains of the damned croquet on the white and black
checkerboard, funereal tiling of the dining room, she runs away as if
she knew herself to be forever pursued. In her room, carefully shutting
the door, she locks herself in and leans on the mirror. For a tooth!...
Quiet! It’s not so bad. She tries to laugh out loud, and she turns
around frightened. Huh? who laughs thusly? Who laughs with a shadow
between their lips? It’s her! Oh! that black star in the middle of that
double white flash! Nothing can be done at this point. And the time is
so distant when she laughed with all her teeth. A wrinkle, this would be
one <em>more</em> thing; a white hair, this would be a <em>new</em> thing. The one
fewer tooth is an irremediable catastrophe; and if she begged the
dentist to replace her own tooth, it would still be a fake tooth! Oh!
she felt it, when it fell between pieces of the croquet, like a little
cold heart that was escaping from her. She has just exhaled everything
in a miniscule detail of herself. Oh! the atrocious reality! Come on!
come on! have courage! She is a reasonable woman, she will not cry, she
will not tell anything, she will have only this interior exclamation,
frightfully sorry: “Lord! Lord!” Because she is pious and has made for
herself a second husband of God at supreme moments of despondency. When
her mother died, she shouted: “Lord!” Inwardly, also, in the same way.
Tomorrow, she must approach the sacraments, she will have a greater
fervor, that’s all, and will not think about it anymore.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, her tongue still thinks about it! With the tip of her
tongue, she performs senseless snakings into that dark corner of her
jaw. She finds there a formidable gap, and she suddenly has, poor woman,
the very absurd vision of a castle of olden times in ruins, gazed upon
during its honeymoon. Yes… she perceives the tower, over there, a
tower which holds at its summit a notched crown, and which hangs, in
thunderstorms, like the unequal jaw of a colossal old...</p>

<p>Her temples are buzzing. If her husband arrived, she would tell him
everything. Incidentally, he is so discreet, so decent, that she really
hopes... to hide everything from him. She walks around, tries to calm
herself by closing her eyes in front of the mirror. Then, it’s finished,
she will no longer laugh. She will no longer open her mouth wide to
swallow an oyster. Suddenly, she stops... And love?... Oh! what a
diabolical joy seizes her in dreaming that she is no longer subject to
the desperate kisses of the honeymoon! And to say that there are wives
who take lovers in order to try to remember those caresses!... How
virtue seems preferable to her today. She rushes toward a drawer, looks
for a small round case, removes a ring from it, then, with almost
material care and full of superstitious fright, she places her tooth on
the black velvet. How white it is, little dead one! Who killed it? It is
still so healthy despite the brown edging. My God! Is it then true? It
is necessary to be carried off a little every day? And the horrible
thing is that there isn’t any other cause for this inexorable, crumbling
(<em>miette à miette</em>) departure than the following: good people must
nonetheless die one day. Oh! right now! A revolver! Some poison!... I
want to be carried off from it completely! And a kind of interior echo
answers her: “You are no longer complete!”</p>

<p>The door is open, her husband gaily enters: “Did you do your
meditations, Bichette?”<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Whenever she must take communion the
following day, he does not get any more familiar with her, for delicate
reasons. He is a serious, affectionate husband, full of pretty
kindnesses without being amorous in the least. She has a half-smile.
“Yes, I meditated... See, do not tease me, I say!” He is seated in
front of her, he pats her thigh for a moment; he wants to chat, to tell
a story, his eyes brilliant. He met the gaze of Sir Silve, that
imbecile... And he speaks quickly, in order to have time to tell
everything before the polite break in conversation. He is having a
quarrel with Silve, the owner of the adjacent estate, and he never
forgets to denigrate his dogs, his cars, his livery. Back in Paris, they
will be excellent comrades again in their circle, but on holiday he
cannot put up with him, because one of them, the neighbor, possesses the
most beautiful pheasants.</p>

<p>Standing in front of him, she wonders if, out of Christian humility, she
must reveal everything to him. But why deteriorate before his eyes? Her
confessor will not force her. And by listening to him she feels herself
enveloped in an icy mood. She is two, and yet, she is alone. Is there
nothing that can carry you, soulmates, beyond your bodies? And suddenly
a sentence sounds like a shot in her distracted ears. Her husband just
said to her, much gentler than the rest: “See, Bichette, I have it in
(<em>je lui garde une dent</em>) for that idiot Silve!”<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> She topples from
the full height of her long chair. A nervous fit twists her. “Bichette!
What have you? Damn it!...” She doesn’t respond at all. He runs to the
bell, which doesn’t vibrate, for an unknown reason, but, while running,
he broke a crystal cornet and the maid suddenly appears, frightened. Now
it undoes her, she is alone; he withdraws, not asking for an
explanation, knowing that she is always nervous on the eve of making her
devotions. She remains alone, she will sleep alone. Oh! so alone with
this ridiculous secret!... And the following day she wakes up bathed in
sweat, she had strange nightmares: it seemed to her that she was chewing
on her own flesh. She prays, she dresses, supports what is attached,
chooses a thick veil, puts the round case in her pocket. She does not
want to part with it. What if they were to search her furniture?... She
steps out of the dense park through a hidden exit, stealthily entering
the church. The old priest, a country priest, a heavy man, believes he
must greet her before beginning the mass. At last, waiting for her, the
host between his raised fat fingers, he murmurs: “My God, let me forget
these vanities!” And she advances, eyelids half-closed, and kneels. Oh!
Oblivion and Consolation! Her whole being is drawn toward the region of
mystical union, where kisses are surrendered without care of the number
of teeth. She receives the host, closes her mouth; but while her tongue,
with a smooth and respectful movement, gently turns over the slice of
divine bread, folds it in half to swallow it faster, she guesses
(<em>devine</em>) and sees that God has stopped... He is still not used to it,
and remains in a corner on the side of the little hole! The poor woman
calls to his aid every last bit of saliva. She frantically departs from
the Holy Table, having the sacrilegious desire to spit despite her
fervor. What! Is it the God of charity who is inflicting such
humiliation? If it was ordinary bread, she would understand, but Him!
Then, she detaches him with a brutal blow of her tongue and suddenly
swallows; God disappears, rushes away as if he were afraid, after
finding out. Her face in her clenched hands, she cries. It ends up
relieving her. As she walks down the shady path of the park, she cries
again, although less desperately. A kind of astonishing dryness rises
from her heart to her eyes. Even though death must announce itself from
time to time, without it, happy people would not think about it. She
contemplates a lily standing there, under a tree with trailing branches,
a lily whose sickly whiteness reminds her of her deceased tooth. With a
deep sigh, she removes the small round box from her pocket, kisses it,
digs up the ground, and thrusts into it the tiny coffin which contains
the first piece of her. Disgusted, she presses with all the strength of
her nervous hands, replaces the moss around the lily, which erases all
trace of the burial. Then, lips trembling, she moves away, with a little
bit of dirt beneath her fingernails...</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>The husband uses the formal <em>vous</em> form in this question, which
explains the following line. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><em>Je lui garde une dent</em> literally means “I’m keeping a tooth for
him,” which is why Bichette reacts in such a way. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Jake Nabasny</name></author><category term="translations" /><category term="rachilde" /><category term="french" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Tooth By Rachilde]]></summary></entry></feed>